Guide to the German Correspondence from the World Wars Collection 1916-1946 MSS 161 MSS.161
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series V: Helmut Riedel
  - [ ], Albert- March 7, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - [Anafel], [ ]- November 2, 1942- December 26, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - [ ], Annemarie- December 21, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Berger, Willy- December 29, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Daum, Oskar- February 26, 1942- August 14, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - [ ], Erich- December 2, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Frank, E.- December 13, 1941- February 27, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Frank, E.- March 30, 1942- March 4, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - Grossmutter (Riedel)- May 2, 1942- May 7, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Habel, Fritz- January 29, 1939- January 27, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Hamel, Hans- March 22, 1942- August 28, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- September 18, 1939- October 28, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- October 30, 1939- November 3, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- November 6, 1939- November 8, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- November 10, 1939- November 14, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- November 15, 1939- November 18, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- November 18, 1939- November 25, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- November 26, 1939- December 2, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- December 3, 1939- December 10, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - December 12, 1939- December 23, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 157)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- December 23, 1939- January 4, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- January 9, 1940- January 16, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- January 21, 1940- January 26, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- January 28, 1940- February 8, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - Heyn, Hildegard- undated (Box 5, Folder 161a)
  - Hofmann, Ilse- October 27, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - Hoffmann, Lotte- August 26, 1941- October 24, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  - Hoffmann, Lotte- undated (Box 5, Folder 163a)
  - Jensen, Lotti- October 17, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 164)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- January 5, 1942- September 13, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- September 23, 1942- October 3, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165a)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- October 4, 1942- October 14, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165b)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- October 21, 1942- November 4, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165c)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- November 8, 1942- November 24, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Klaussner, Ursula- November 29, 1942- March 21, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 165e)
  - Knauss, Rudolf- January 4, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Lars, Martin- March 2, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165g)
  - Lelumka, M.- April 2, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 165h)
  - Linke, Anneliese- February 25, 1941- April 11, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165i)
  - Linke, Anneliese- April 29, 1941- July 17, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165j)
  - Linke, Anneliese- August 9, 1941- August 22, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 165k)
  - Lunkwitz, Eolith- March 8, 1941- September 24, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165l)
  - Madicke, Adele- April 28, 1941- December 23, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165m)
  - Madicke, Horst- May 24, 1941- December 9, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 165n)
  - Meischner, Elfriede- September 10, 1941- November 19, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 166)
  - Meischner, Elfriede- November 24, 1941- December 28, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 167)
  - Meischner, Elfriede- January 6, 1942- February 14, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - Meischner, Elfriede- February 21, 1942- April 11, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - Raible, Annemarie- April 8, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 170)
  - [Rasa], [Ulm]- September 24, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 171)
  - Richter, Werner- April 16, 1941- July 27, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 172)
  - Richter, Werner- August 17, 1941- October 5, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 173)
  - Riedel, Eberhard- November 18, 1939- February 23, 1942, 1939-1942 (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Riedel, Hans- February 16, 1942- March 1, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - Riedel, Helmut- October 25, 1939- January 20, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 176)
  - Riedel, Helmut- March 2, 1940- June 5, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 177)
  - Riedel, Helmut- June 8, 1940- July 13, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 178)
  - Riedel, Helmut- August 26, 1940- May 5, 1941, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 179)
  - Riedel, Helmut- May 2, 1941- June 29, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Riedel, Helmut- July 24, 1941- December 6, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 181)
  - Riedel, Helmut- January 15, 1942- April 29, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Riedel, Helmut- undated (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Riedel, Helmut- undated (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Riedel, Helmut- undated (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Riedel, Kurt- November 2, 1939- June 5, 1941, 1939-1941 (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - Riedel, Kurt- July 18, 1941- November 23, 1943, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 187)
  - Riedel, Kurt- undated (Box 6, Folder 187a)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- December 4, 1939- June 16, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 188)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- February 24, 1941- July 16, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 189)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- July 25, 1941- August 10, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 190)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- October 6, 1941- March 10, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 191)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- March 14, 1942- April 12, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- July 8, 1942- October 6, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 193)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- October 11, 1942- October 25, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 194)
  - Riedel, Lisbeth (Mutter)- October 28, 1942- December 9, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Riedel, Paul- February 20, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - [Rofler]- undated (Box 6, Folder 197)
  - Schneider, Traudel (Gertraude)- January 2, 1940- November 19, 1941, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 198)
  - Schneider, Traudel (Gertraude)- December 30, 1941- October 17, 1943, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 199)
  - Schubert, Else- November 19, 1939- August 19, 1943, 1939-1943 (Box 6, Folder 200)
  - Singer, H.- May 1, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 201)
  - Swoboda, Elfriede- July 29, 1941- May 7, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 202)
  - Telle, Elfriede- January 28, 1942- May 13, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 203)
  - Vater (Riedel)- December 10, 1939- April 27, 1941, 1939-1941 (Box 6, Folder 204)
  - Vater (Riedel)- May 11, 1941- August 21, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Vater (Riedel)- February 16, 1942- April 14, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 206)
  - Vater (Riedel)- October 6, 1941- March 14, 1943, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 207)
  - [Wander], Werner- March 9, 1941- May 19, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 208)
  - [Wander], Werner- June 15, 1941- January 9, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 209)
  - [ ], Willy and Gertrud (Onkel and Tante)- January 15, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 210)
  - Wittig, M.- September 27, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 211)
  - Wolf, Walter- December 29, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 212)
  - Unidentified- December 13, 1939- August 14, 1941, 1939-1941 (Box 6, Folder 213)
  - Unidentified- August 22, 1941- September 26, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 214)
  - Unidentified- April 11, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 215)
  - Unidentified- undated (Box 6, Folder 215a)
  - Envelopes- 1939-1942 (Box 6, Folder 216)
- Series VI: Pietro Schiavi and Shirley Messinger
  Series VI contains the letters of a young Italian, Pietro Schiavi, to his Rhode Island penpal, Shirley Messinger. The correspondence of this series is in English, not German. The letters, which date from April 1935 to January 1945, trace Schiavi's trajectory from student to soldier to prisoner of war in Germany. Schivai signs his name first as Pietro, then as Pete and Piero; he also begins to refer to Shirley as Wally. The series contains the various "gifts" that Schiavi sent - a pressed flower, photos, newspaper clippings, and a postcard book. The series also contains memorabilia from Messinger's high school and college (Pembroke) years and a manuscript, "Facts about Pietro Schiavi," which includes an inventory of "Letters Received."
  - Schiavi, Pietro- April 27, 1935- September 18, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 217)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- February 29, 1936- December 14, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 218)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- January 28, 1937- August 17, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 219)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- September 23, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 220)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- December 18, 1937- April 28, 1939, 1937-1939 (Box 7, Folder 221)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- July 9, 1939- November 24, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 222)
  - Schiavi, Pietro- December 6, 1939- January 31, 1945, 1939-1945 (Box 7, Folder 223)
  - Schedule for Freshmen and Transfer Students, Pembroke College, Brown University, October 27- November 3, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 224)
  - Miniature Flyer for a production of "A Foul Plot That Failed" by the G.P. Club, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 225)
  - Newspaper clipping from a listing of "Society" events, undated (Box 8, Folder 226)
  - "Facts About Pietro Schiavi," Inventory of "Letters Received," and outline of Mussolini's Life, Manuscript of Shirley Messinger, [1940] (Box 8, Folder 227)
  - Invitation and Materials for induction into the Providence Assembly, NO. 1, Order of the Rainbow for Girls- March 1937 (Box 8, Folder 228)
  - Postcards depicting Abbiatgrasso, Roma, and Ethiopia, annotated by Pietro Schiavi for Shirley Messinger, undated (Box 8, Folder 229)
  - Report Cards of Shirley Messinger, 3rd Grade to High School, 1930-1940 (Box 8, Folder 230)
  - Date Book ("Engagements") of Shirley Messiniger for the 1940-1 Academic Year at Pembroke College, 1940-1941 (Box 8, Folder 231)
  - Dance Card for East Providence High School's Class of 1938 Senior Prom (Box 8, Folder 232)
  - "Roma: Parte IIa," small fold-out picture book of Roman sights with brief histories of each in four languages, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 233)
  - "Algebra Notebook of Rules," handwritten by Shirley Messinger on small, spiral memo pad, undated (Box 8, Folder 234)
  - Badge for East Providence High School, undated (Box 8, Folder 235)
  - Pennant for East Providence High School, undated (Box 8, Folder 236)
  - Charms awarded to Shirley Messinger for "Service" and "Petitions", undated (Box 8, Folder 237)
  - Daily Planners of Shirley Messinger, 1941-1943 (Box 8, Folder 238)
  - Remington, Pearl M.T. (Assistant Superintendent for the Department of Public Schools, East Providence, RI)- letter of congratulations on finalist standing in the Good Citizen Pilgrimage competition, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 239)
  - Photo of Pietro Schiavi's brother, "where we go to bathe", undated (Box 8, Folder 240)
- Series VII: Eugen Uhl and Josef (Sepp) Jung
  Series VII, Sub-series A contains roughly 450 pieces of correspondence dating from 1936 to 1946, with the majority of the letters dating from 1942 to 1944. The letters center around Eugen and Waldemar Uhl, both of whom were in the German army, and their parents in St. Ingbert (Saar), Ernst and Therese Uhl. Waldemar's last letter home is from June 23, 1941. The letters from Ernst and Therese begin in late 1942; almost all are addressed to Eugen. It appears that Ernst Uhl successfully petitioned for his son Eugen's removal from the front to "[a less dangerous post]" in March of 1943 (see Atbacher, March 18, 1943, and Hauptmann [...], March 22, 1943). The majority of letters in this subseries are between Eugen and his parents. Interspersed with the Uhl family letters were about 35 letters addressed to Obergefreiter [Corporal] Josef (or Sepp, with the familiar form Seppel, which can be abbreviated as Sepp'l) Jung. No immediate relationship between Jung and Uhl is apparent. These 35 letters compose Sub-series B.
  - Subseries A: Eugen Uhl
    - A[]bacher, J.; Major, Batl. 12- March 18, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 241)
    - Benesch, Eberhard- October 13, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Hauptmann and Kompaniefuhrer of Batl. 12, 2. Kompanie- March 22, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - Hel[]en, R.- March 31, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 244)
    - Hermann, Karl- May 15, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - Hugo, Adalbero- January 3, 1943- February 21, 1945, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - Hugo, Alois and the family- January 11, 1943- November 9, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 247)
    - Hugo, Alois and the family- January 31, 1944- December 12, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 248)
    - Hugo, Arthur- July 26, 1942- January 29, 1945, 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 249)
    - Hugo, Ernstl (see also Hugo, Alois and the family)- May 17, 1942- March 3, 1944, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 250)
    - Hugo, Hans- August 13, 1942- October 27, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 251)
    - Hugo, Joseff- January 10, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 252)
    - Hugo, K[a]thi and Leni- January 10, 1943- March 11, 1945, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 253)
    - Hugo, [Maria]- September 17, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 254)
    - Hugo, Ruth- September 15, 1943- December 15, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - Kessler, Rudolf- February 4, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 256)
    - Klein, [Hans]- December 21, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 257)
    - Leder, Babette and Fritz- January 2, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 258)
    - [Michel], K. Leo- October 14, 1942- June 6, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 9, Folder 259)
    - Muller, E.- October 12, 1943- October 31, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - Muller, the family- January 18, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 261)
    - Oberstaatsanwalt bei dem Landgericht in Frankenthal (Pfalz)- March 25, 1943, April 9, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 262)
    - Pfeilstucker, Jette- October 20, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 263)
    - Plein, Theo.- April 19, 1943- August 5, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 264)
    - Rosemann, Kurt- June 1, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 265)
    - Sander, Marlis- October 24, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 266)
    - Schmitz, W.- January 3, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 267)
    - Schroder, Emma- February 21, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 268)
    - Shroder, [Lotti]- December 14, 1943- February 23, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 269)
    - Stumpf, Rud.- September 9, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 270)
    - Suss, Leo[pold]- August 25, 1943- March 9, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 271)
    - Trauthering, K.- November 27, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 272)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese ("Papa" and "Mama")- December 15, 1942- January 14, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 273)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- January 21, 1943- March 4, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 274)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- March 8, 1943- May 6, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 275)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- May 10, 1943- July 2, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 276)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- July 5, 1943- September 21, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 277)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- September 22, 1943- November 10, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 278)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- November 16, 1943- January 14, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 10, Folder 279)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- January 16, 1944- March 2, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 280)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- March 15, 1944- May 12, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 281)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- May 14, 1944- July 2, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 282)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- July 6, 1944- August 18, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 283)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- August 19, 1944- September 24, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 284)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- September 25, 1944- November 23, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 285)
    - Uhl, Ernst and Therese- November 28, 1944- January 5, 1945, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 286)
    - Uhl, Eugen- May 26, 1940- January 13, 1943, 1940-1943 (Box 11, Folder 287)
    - Uhl, Eugen- January 31, 1943- March 22, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 288)
    - Uhl, Eugen- April 5, 1943- May 16, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 289)
    - Uhl, Eugen- June 15, 1943- July 30, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 290)
    - Uhl, Eugen- August 1, 1943- October 10, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 291)
    - Uhl, Eugen- October 10, 1943- November 7, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 292)
    - Uhl, Eugen- November 8, 1943- December 16, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 293)
    - Uhl, Eugen- December 20, 1943- March 1, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 11, Folder 294)
    - Uhl, Eugen- March 6, 1944- April 21, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 295)
    - Uhl, Eugen- April 22, 1944- June 16, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 296)
    - Uhl, Eugen- June 17, 1944- July 28, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 297)
    - Uhl, Eugen- July 29, 1944- September 9, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 298)
    - Uhl, Eugen- September 11, 1944- October 20, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 299)
    - Uhl, Eugen- November 8, 1944- December 21, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 300)
    - Uhl, Eugen- December 23, 1944- February 6, 1945, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 301)
    - Uhl, Eugen- February 6, 1945- March 3, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 302)
    - Uhl, Eugen (II, Uncle of Eugen Uhl)- July 16, 1942- July 16, 1944, 1942-1944 (Box 11, Folder 303)
    - Uhl, Otto- December 27, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 304)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- April 2, 1936- December 10, 1939, 1936-1939 (Box 12, Folder 305)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- December 16, 1939- January 14, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 306)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- January 18, 1940- March 9, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 307)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- March 14, 1940- April 30, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 308)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- May 3, 1940- June 21, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 309)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- June 26, 1940- August 20, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 310)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- September 1, 1940- October 2, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 311)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- October 7, 1940- November 25, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 312)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- December 3, 1940- January 11, 1944, 1940-1944 (Box 12, Folder 313)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- January 14, 1941- February 16, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 314)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- February 17, 1941- March 23, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 315)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- March 25, 1941- May 18, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 316)
    - Uhl, Waldemar- May 25, 1941- June 23, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 317)
    - Uhl, [ ]- August 10, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 318)
    - Werner, Herman- September 2, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 319)
    - Wolgast, Prof. Dr.- February 14, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 320)
    - [ ], [P. Romwald]- December 22, 1943- April 3, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 13, Folder 321)
    - Unidentified- October 23, 1941- November 24, 1943, 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 322)
  - Subseries B: Josef (Sepp) Jung
    - Banilloy, Annette- January 6, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 323)
    - Gl[u]ck, Ruth- November 27, 1942- November 5, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 13, Folder 324)
    - Grass, Alfons- April 4, 1940- August 25, 1944, 1940-1944 (Box 13, Folder 325)
    - Grass, Josef- December 29, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 326)
    - Grieges, Hugo- July 28, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 327)
    - Hadrich, Traute- April 21, 1944- June 2, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 328)
    - Hickmann, Gerda- May 14, 1944- March 16, 1946, 1944-1946 (Box 13, Folder 329)
    - Jahns, Gerda- April 27, 1944- July 14, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 330)
    - Jung, Albertus- May 18, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 331)
    - Klein, Hein- June 17, 1942- February 27, 1944, 1942-1944 (Box 13, Folder 332)
    - Lehberg, Anni- May 17, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 333)
    - Marz, Oswald- November 2, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 334)
    - Schappert, Fr. Julius- May 30, 1940- June 12, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 335)
    - Schnuss, [ ]- July 3, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 336)
    - [Sinsner], Lisl- March 27, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 337)
    - Weingeder, Heinz- December 15, 1942- December 30, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 338)
    - Wittcheu, Marga- April 5, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 339)
- Series VIII: Jakob Werle
  The majority of the letters in this series are to Jakob Werle. The remaining letters are addressed either to the Werle Family or sent by Jakob himself. The reader will notice that Werle's hand is radically different in the letter of February 14, 1944 from the military hospital at Wenden due to his injuries from a grenade explosion in Russia. From the German hospital in Wenden, Werle was transferred to a military hospital in Choroszcz, near Bialystok, in Poland. From Poland, he was moved back to Germany, to the hospital at Erfurt, from where his last letter, the latest dated (February 15, 1945) letter in this series, was sent.
  - Althaus, Kurt- June 4, 1942- April 5, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 340)
  - Becher, Tilly- March 31, 1942- April 3, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 341)
  - Bier, Hedwig- July 28, 1942- June 6, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 342)
  - Dinges, Albert- November 18, 1942- March 4, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 343)
  - Dinges, [ ]- October 29, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 344)
  - Grotsch, August- December 12, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 345)
  - Hoffmann, Gunther- February 25, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 346)
  - Hoffmann, Gunther- February 25, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 346)
  - Kreishandwerkerschaft Birkenfeld-Baumholder- May 10, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 347)
  - Kuhn, Elisabeth- February 6, 1942- April 6, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 348)
  - Laas, Sauni- February 22, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 349)
  - Lanz: Heinrich Lanz Aktiengesselschaft- May 10, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 350)
  - Leinges, Leo- December 8, 1942- April 5, 1944, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 351)
  - Muller, Jakob- November 3, 1941- May 17, 1944, 1941-1944 (Box 14, Folder 352)
  - Schmidt, August- October 20, 1941- October 4, 1943, 1941-1943 (Box 14, Folder 353)
  - Schmidt, August- undated (Box 14, Folder 353a)
  - Schmidt, Robert- July 15, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 354)
  - Schmitt, Hedwig- July 24, 1942- August 17, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 355)
  - Schmitt, Willibrand- March 1, 1944- June 13, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 356)
  - Schneider, [ ]- March 8, 1942- June 9, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 357)
  - Schuck, Alois and the Schuck Family- October 8, 1941- June 16, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 14, Folder 358)
  - Schuck, Alois and the Schuck Family- July 13, 1942- March 14, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 359)
  - Schuck, Alois and the Schuck Family- March 21, 1943- June 28, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 360)
  - Schuck, Alois and the Schuck Family- August 1, 1943- January 3, 1945, 1943-1945 (Box 14, Folder 361)
  - Schuck, Elisabeth- October 15, 1941- August 16, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 14, Folder 362)
  - Seutner, Georg- November 27, 1942- March 19, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 363)
  - Spader, Waldemar- February 1, 1942- September 11, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 364)
  - Spader, Waldemar- October 16, 1942- June 27, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 365)
  - Su-[ ]rf, [ ]- December 10, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 366)
  - Wagner, Albert- March 22, 1942- March 15, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 367)
  - Werle, Alfons- November 23, 1941- June 30, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 368)
  - Werle, Alois- May 5, 1942- January 30, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 15, Folder 369)
  - Werle, Alois- February 2, 1943- June 12, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 370)
  - Werle, Alois- June 16, 1943- December 14, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 371)
  - Werle, Jakob- September 16, 1942- November 16, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 372)
  - Werle, Jakob- March 2, 1943- February 16, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 373)
  - Werle, Jakob- February 20, 1944- February 15, 1945, 1944-1945 (Box 15, Folder 374)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- February 1, 1941- February 22, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 15, Folder 375)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- March 1, 1942- May 17, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 376)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- July 12, 1942- August 30, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 377)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- September 16, 1942- December 21, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 378)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- January 1, 1943- March 7, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 379)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- March 14, 1943- April 30, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 380)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- May 6, 1943- July 18, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 381)
  - Werle, Joseph and the Werle family- undated (Box 15, Folder 381a)
  - Werle, Maria- January 3, 1942- February 21, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 15, Folder 382)
  - Werle, Maria- undated (Box 15, Folder 382a)
  - Werle, Maria- March 11, 1943- July 20, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 383)
  - Wernig, Hans- November 17, 1941- December 28, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 15, Folder 384)
  - [ ], Agnes- April 29, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 385)
  - [ ], Agnes- undated (Box 15, Folder 385a)
  - [ ], Friedrich- March 10, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 386)
  - Unidentified- undated (Box 15, Folder 387)
- Series IX: Gottlob Zieher